A Guide to the Henry Luce Foundation records, Michael Gilligan Presidential Files FA1724
Rockefeller Archive Center
Henry Luce Foundation records, Michael Gilligan Presidential Files
1998-2019
Rockefeller Archive Center
Henry Luce Foundation
FA1724
3.52 Cubic Feet 8 letter-size document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The Henry Luce Foundation was established by Henry R. Luce in 1936. As a New York-based nonprofit organization, the Luce Foundation awards grants in American Art, Asian studies, Higher Education, Theology, and supports the Clare Boothe Luce Program for women in science, mathematics, and engineering.
Michael Gilligan serves as President of the Henry Luce Foundation after being elected to the position in December 2002.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Henry Luce Foundation in 2019.
Arrangement
The Henry Luce Foundation records, Michael Gilligan Presidential Files are arranged as received:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1998-2019
Series 2: Presentations, Speeches, and Reports, 1999-2019
Scope and Contents
The Henry Luce Foundation records, Michael Gilligan Presidential Files contain correspondence, presentation, speeches, and reports. Major topics include theological education and philanthropy, with an emphasis on non-profits and their relationships with colleges and universities.
PHILANTHROPY--U.S.A.; Religions; International relations; Education, Higher; Theology
- Correspondence, 1998-2019; 1
  - 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Memos to Henry Luce III, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Memos to Henry Luce III, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 10-14)
  - 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 15-19)
  - Pope Benedict XVI and Rabbi Arthur Schneier at Park East Synagogue, 2008 April 18 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - 2010-2011 (Box 4, Folder 18-22)
  - 2012-2014 (Box 5, Folder 23-28)
  - 2015-2019 (Box 6, Folder 29-33)
- Presentations, Speeches, and Reports, 1999-2019; 2
  - Arthur Vining Davis Foundation - Yale, New Haven, Connecticut, 2013 May 3 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Asia Foundation Fellows Meeting - Henry Luce Foundation, New York, New York, 2016 September 20 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Asia Foundation Hayden Williams' Memorial - San Francisco, California, 2016 May 23 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Asia Foundation Board Dinner - New York, New York, 2013 May 13 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Association of Theological Schools Biennial Meeting - Chicago, Illinois, 2006 June 24 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    Scope and Contents
    The 1996 Accrediting Standards: Reflections a Decade Later
  - Association of Theological Schools Dan Aleshire Retirement Celebration - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 2017 April 22-24 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Association of Theological Schools/DIAP Workshops - Savannah, Georgia and Quebec, Canada, 1999-2002 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    Making Your Case in a Grant Proposal workshop
  - ATSEA Keynote - Malaysia, 2001 November 22 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    Blessed Ties That Bind: Theological Education in a Global Market Economy
  - Azusa Pacific University - Azusa, California, 1999 October 22 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    Leadership Ministry in the 21st Century
  - Baruch College - New York, New York, 2011 November 30 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    Panel of Non-Profit Leaders
  - Brown University, Watson Institute - Providence, Rhode Island, 2010 November 5-6 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    Conference talk with Kit Luce.
  - Center for Curatorial Leadership Fellows Meeting, Kress Foundation - New York, New York, 2018 January 10 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    Foundation Craft
  - Central Baptist Theological Seminary Commencement - Shawnee, Kansas, 2012 May 11 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Chung Chi College Assembly, Chinese University of Hong Kong - Hong Kong, 2012 April 13 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    Practicing in the Presence of God, Christian Higher Education in Asia
  - Church of the Holy Apostles - New York, New York, 2006 September 24 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - College of the Atlantic - Bar Harbor, Maine, 2017 August 21 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    Preparing Leaders in American Life: What's the Role of Religion?
  - John Cook Memorial - Yale Divinity School, New Haven, Connecticut, 2019 June 17 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Council for Advancement and Support for Education (CASE) - New York, New York, 2012 June 2 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    Foundations Relations Conference
  - Council of Independent Colleges - New York, New York, 2012 October 9 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    Foundations and Institutions in Partnership to Advance Independent Colleges and Universities, Annual Conversation of College Presidents and Foundation Officers at TIAA-CREF.
  - Council of Independent Colleges - Florida, 2018 January 5 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    Foundation Philanthropy
  - Council of Independent Colleges - New York, New York, 2011 November 5 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    Advancing the Case for Liberal Arts
  - Council of Independent Colleges - Florida, 2010 January 5 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    Panel on Foundations -- CIC Presidents Institute
  - Council of Independent Colleges - New York, New York, 2004 September 20 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    Converstaion between Foundation Officers and College/University Presidents, TIAA-CREF
  - Development and Institutional Advancement Program (DIAP) Conference - New Orleans, Louisiana, 2009 February 5-7 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    Institutional Advancement, the Foundation, and Times Like These
  - Episcopal Divinity School - Cambridge, Massachusetts, 2012 October 19 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    Christian Higher Education and Interfaith Activism
  - Ewha-Luce International Seminar - Seoul, Korea, 2019 July 12 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    ELIS Commencement Exercises
  - Ewha-Luce International Seminar - Seoul, Korea, 2015 June 30 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    Open Forum: ELIS, Expanding Horizons
  - Hiram College, Garfield Society Dinner - Hiram, Ohio, 2009 October 23 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    Philanthropy in Times of Stress
  - General Theological Seminary - New York, New York, 2007 April 11 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    ...For the Church in a Changing World
  - Georgetown University, FADICA Institute - Washington, D.C., 2003 June 7-9 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    Should You Know Something about Theology If You Do Religious Philanthropy?
  - Graduate Theological Union - Berkeley, California, 2016 May 25-26 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    Celebrating Judith Berling
  - Hartford Seminary, Heidi Hadsell Retirement - Hartford, Connecticut, 2018 April 29-30 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Hartford Seminary, Commencement - Hartford, Connecticut, 2016 May 13 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    Another Day the Lord Has Made
  - Hood Theological Seminary, Commencement - Salisbury, North Carolina, 2003 May 10; Contains photographs (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Interfaith Association of Central Ohio - Powell, Ohio, 2004 October 12 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    Engaging Religious Diversity: Three Promising Developments
  - International Christian University, 60th Anniversary Chapel - Tokyo, Japan, 2013 June 11 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    Seeking Truth, Finding Freedom: The Legacy and Promise of International Christian University
  - Justo Gonzalez Center Dedication - Orlando, Florida, 2011 October 21-22 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - LaGuardia Community College - Long Island City, New York, 2018 May 2 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    Social Justice Panel
  - LaGuardia Community College, Commencement - Long Island City, New York, 2010 September 21 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Lancaster Theological Seminary - Lancaster, Pennsylvania, 2011 February 9-10 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    Knowing about Religion and Practicing Foreign Policy: A Challenge for US Leaders, Gregory Lecture
  - Lancaster Theological Seminary, Consultation - Berkeley, California, 2019 January 14-17 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    Current and Future Directions in Theological Education
  - Lingnan Foundation Trustees Meeting/Dinner, Keynote Address - Costa Mesa, California, 2019 May 13 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    Educating for Uncertain Futures: A Challenge that China and the United States Share
  - Marlboro College - Marlboro, Vermont, 2019 February 12-14 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    Windham World Affairs Council informal presentation
  - Mellon Foundation Colloquium - New York, New York, 2013 March 14 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    The Arc of Philanthropy
  - Memorial for John (Jack) C. Evans - Old Lyme, Connecticut, 2016 March 5 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Mepkin Abbey. Francis Kline Memorial - Moncks Corner, South Carolina, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Nazarene Theological Seminary, Global Consortium - Kansas City, Missouri, 2015 April 10 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - New Brunswick Seminary, Commencement - New Brunswick, New Jersey, 2004 May 23 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - New York Regional Association of Grantmakers (NYRAG) - New York, New York, 2005 March (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Norman Rockwell Museum, Crystal Bridges Museum of Art - Bentonville, Arizona, 2013 March 6 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Olivet Nazarene University - Bourbonnais, Illinois, 2002 August 22 (Box 8, Folder 84)
    Teaching and Learning at the Heart of the Church
  - Park-Rawle Wedding - New York, New York, 2016 May 21 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Perkins School of Theology - Dallas, Texas, 2014 September 12 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Pulitzer Center - Washington, D.C., 2019 June 7-9 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    Beyond Religion
  - St. Vladimir's Orthodox Theological Seminary, Retreat - Crestwood, New York, 2000 December 6 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - South Pacific Association of Theological Schools (SPATS) - Nuku'alofa, Tonga, 2004 April 2 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    Enhancing Quality Theological Education in Oceania
  - Spring Arbor University, Commencement - Spring Arbor, Michigan, 2004 October 2 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Tanenbaum Center Gala - New York, New York, 2019 June 19 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia, Candy Eng Memorial - New York, New York, 2017 January 17 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - United Church of Christ Seminaries - Cleveland, Ohio, 2013 February 20 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - United Theological Seminary of the Twin Cities, Consultation on Theology and the Arts - Minneapolis, Minnesota, 2002 September 26 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - United States Department of State Panel - Washington, D.C., 2016 September 26 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    Philanthropic Perspectives on Religion and Diplomacy
  - Vanderbilt University - Nashville, Tennessee, 2005 October 14 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    Luce Chancellor's Chair
  - President's Reports to the Directors of the Henry Luce Foundation, 2003-2019 (Box 8, Folder 97)